Indiana University School of Letters Director's records, 1947-1979 C36
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University School of Letters Director's records
1947-1979
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University. School of Letters
C36
3.8 cubic feet 5 boxes
The School of Letters was originally created by John Crowe Ransom, F.O. Matthiessen, and Lionel Trilling as a part of the School of English at Kenyon College. When support from the Rockefeller Foundation ended, the program moved to Indiana University in the summer of 1951. Collection consists of the records of the Director of the School of Letters 1947-1979, organized in four series. The bulk of the collection is comprised of office files and correspondence between director Newton P. Stallknecht and faculty and guest lecturers. Prominent correspondents include a number of famous American poets and critics such as Randall Jarrell and John Crowe Ransom, as well as noted foreign scholars including the French existentialist philosopher Jean Wahl. Also included in the collection are a sample of student files and files representing Stallknecht's general university activities in his role as director of the School of Letters.
Access Restrictions
The Student Files Series is closed to researchers.
Advance notice required for access.
Historical Note
The School of Letters was originally created by John Crowe Ransom, F.O. Matthiessen, and Lionel Trilling as a part of the School of English at Kenyon College. When support from the Rockefeller Foundation ended, the program moved to Indiana University in the summer of 1951. Supported by a similar grant from IU, the School of Letters began as a summer program, but expanded into a full-year program in the fall of 1961. The School of Letters remained distinct from the English department because of its contribution to the study of literary theory and criticism. According to Stallknecht, The School of Letters emphasized practical criticism over the biographical and historical approaches to the study of literature common in the departments of English and Comparative Literature. The program grew to international acclaim and was able to attract guest lecturers from the eminent scholars of the world. The program was phased out after the 1972 session, following Stallknecht's resignation as Director.
Arrangement
Records organized in four series: Faculty files, Student files, Office files, and University/General files.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the records of the Director of The School of Letters, incumbent Newton P. Stallknecht. The records date between 1947 and 1979, although Stallknecht was only officially the director from 1953 to 1972. The bulk of the collection is comprised of office files from the School of Letters and correspondence between Stallknecht and other faculty and guest lecturers. The diverse faculty correspondence files demonstrate the excellence of the IU School of Letters and the international acclaim it received. The collection includes correspondence with numerous famous American poets and critics, such as as Randall Jarrell (1914-1965) and John Crowe Ransom (1888-1974), as well as noted foreign scholars, including the French Existentialist philosopher, Jean Wahl (1888-1974). The collection also includes a sample of School of Letters student files and files representing his general university activities as Director of the School of Letters.
Acquisition Information
Accession 2000/055, 2017/004.465
Provenance
Transferred to the Archives from the IU Lilly Library in 2000.
The School of Letters annual bulletins were transferred from the IU Archives publications collection in April 2018.
Universities and colleges --Indiana --Bloomington --Administration --History --20th century --Sources.; Criticism --Study and teaching (Higher) --Indiana --Bloomington.; Philosophy teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; Literature teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; Jarrell, Randall, 1914-1965 -- Correspondence; Ransom, John Crowe, 1888-1974 -- Correspondence; Wahl, Jean André, 1888-1974 -- Correspondence; Indiana University -- Administration -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Indiana University. School of Letters -- Archives; Indiana University. School of Letters -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. School of Letters -- History -- Sources; Stallknecht, Newton P. (Newton Phelps), 1906-1981 -- Archives; Stallknecht, Newton P. (Newton Phelps), 1906-1981 -- Correspondence
- Faculty Files, 1949-1973
  - Ashton, John W., 1950-1969 (Box 1)
  - Band, Arnold J., 1969 (Box 1)
  - Beker, Miroslav, 1966-1973 (Box 1)
  - Benzinger, James, 1949-1955 (Box 1)
  - Berryman, John, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Blackmur, Richard, 1950-1965 (Box 1)
  - Brady, Dr. Donald J., 1964-1972 (Box 1)
  - Brumbaugh, Robert Sherrick, 1949-1960 (Box 1)
  - Brumm, Ursula, 1966-1972 (Box 1)
  - Burke, Kenneth (Box 1)
    - 1950-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1952-1958 (Box 1)
      Conditions Governing Access
      (RESTRICTED)
  - Cambon, Glauco, 1959-1973 (Box 1)
  - Carmichael, Douglas, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Cavell, Stanley, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - Chase, Richard, 1950-1962 (Box 1)
  - Cooperman, Stanley, 1957-1966 (Box 1)
  - Cox, James, 1958-1972 (Box 1)
  - Cunningham, James V., 1961 (Box 1)
  - Ellmann, Richard, 1955-1971 (Box 1)
  - Erlich, Victor, 1958-1961 (Box 1)
  - Fergusson, Francis, 1950-1971 (Box 1)
  - Fite, Warner, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Fitzgerald, Robert, 1951-1972 (Box 1)
  - Frenz, Horst, 1969-1972 (Box 1)
  - Friar, Kimon, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Frye, H. Northrop, 1955-1971 (Box 1)
  - Fukuda, Rikutaro, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Hassan, Ihab H., 1952-1964 (Box 1)
  - Honig, Edwin, 1966-1969 (Box 1)
  - Howard, Vernon, 1963-1973 (Box 1)
  - Howe, Irving, 1952-1961 (Box 1)
  - Hrushovski, Benjamin, 1968-1973 (Box 1)
  - Hsia, C. T., 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - Jarrell, Randall, 1952-1966 (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Helen Armstead, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Kazin, Alfred, 1950-1961 (Box 1)
  - Kermode, Frank, 1962-1972 (Box 1)
  - Kurzweil, Baruch, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Lang, Hans J., 1962-1969 (Box 1)
  - Lewis, R.W.B., 1951-1971 (Box 1)
  - McHugh, Roger, 1965-1973 (Box 1)
  - McKinnon, Richard N., 1955-1969 (Box 1)
  - Marcus, Steven, 1960-1970 (Box 1)
  - Matthews, Jackson, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - Moore, Geoffrey H., 1969-1972 (Box 1)
  - Mueller, Martin, 1964-1972 (Box 1)
  - Perkins, Robert, 1962-1973 (Box 1)
  - Rago, Henry, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
  - Rahv, Phillip, 1958-1971 (Box 1)
  - Ransom, John Crowe (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955-1967 (Box 1)
  - Rice, Phillip Blair, 1950-1961 (Box 1)
  - Rupp, Richard, 1959-1973 (Box 1)
  - Schawrtz, Delmore, 1950-1970 (Box 2)
  - Shapiro, Karl, 1955-1968 (Box 2)
  - Steiner, George, 1962-1971 (Box 2)
  - Stiernotte, Alfred P., 1957-1960 (Box 2)
  - Tate, Allen, 1950-1973 (Box 2)
  - Trilling, Lionel, 1950-1972 (Box 2)
  - Wahl, Jean, 1949-1955 (Box 2)
  - Warren, Austin, 1954-1971 (Box 2)
  - Wellek, Rene, 1950-1970 (Box 2)
  - Whitehall, Harold, 1952-1961 (Box 2)
  - Wood, Ledger, 1949-1956 (Box 2)
- Student Files, 1951-1974
  Scope and Contents
  Files in this series are restricted and closed to researchers. Please contact the University Archivist with any further questions.
  - Anderson, Paul, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Feldman, Stephen K., 1952-1958 (Box 2)
  - Fogel, Aaron, 1965-1968 (Box 2)
  - Gnarowski, Michael, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - Green, Jesse D., 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - Haber, Herbert Robert, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
  - Hosek, Chaviva, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Kaminsky, Marc, 1963-1965 (Box 2)
  - Kopp, Melisande, 1964-1969 (Box 2)
  - Maes-Jelinek, Hena, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Momburger, Philip, 1959-1961 (Box 2)
  - Smith, Shirley J., 1964-1974 (Box 2)
  - Sullivan, Sister M. Davida, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Students (Box 2)
    - School of Letters, 1951-1970 (Box 2)
    - Comparative Literature, 1964-1973 (Box 2)
    - Other, 1967-1971 (Box 2)
- School of Letters Office Files, 1948-1979
  - Academic Appointments for Summer, 1966-1968 (Box 2)
  - Address Lists, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Advertising -Magazines (Box 2)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Annual Meeting - Senior Fellows (Box 2)
    - 1953-1964 (Box 2)
    - 1965-1971 (Box 2)
  - Budget (Box 2)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Proposed, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
  - Bulletin - School of Letters, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, 1951-1972 (Box 5)
  - Class Lists, 1969-1973 (Box 2)
  - Class Reading Lists, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence - General (Box 2)
    - 1955-1962 (Box 2)
    - 1963-1973 (Box 2)
  - Course Descriptions, 1951-1972 (Box 2)
  - Course Syllabi, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
  - Courses Added, 1964-1972 (Box 2)
  - Department of the School of Letters, 1961-1972 (Box 3)
  - Education Personnel Development Act, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Enrollment (Box 3)
    - 1951-1968 (Box 3)
    - 1969-1972 (Box 3)
  - Evening Forums, 1951-1971 (Box 3)
  - Executive Actions, 1952-1971 (Box 3)
  - Form Letters, 1953-1968 (Box 3)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships (Box 3)
    - 1962-1968 (Box 3)
    - 1969-1972 (Box 3)
  - Foundation - Lilly Endowment, 1951-1960 (Box 3)
  - Housing, 1950-1971 (Box 3)
  - International Activities Newsletter, 1964-1966 (Box 3)
  - Inquiries, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Kenyon School of English, 1948-1951 (Box 3)
  - Lecturers (Box 3)
    - Guest, 1964-1967 (Box 3)
    - 1968-1974 (Box 3)
  - M.A. Degree - School of Letters, 1951-1967 (Box 3)
  - Majors in the School of Letters, 1951-1967 (Box 3)
  - Minors in the School of Letters, 1968-1971 (Box 3)
  - Office Procedure, undated (Box 3)
  - Organization - School of Letters, 1950-1951 (Box 3)
  - Payroll Record - Summer Instructors, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
  - Ph.D. Exam -School of Letters Minor, 1954-1964 (Box 3)
  - Physical Plant - Repairs, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Program Development, 1969-1973 (Box 3)
  - Prospective Instructors, 1959-1971 (Box 3)
  - Reserve Lists for Books (Box 3)
    - 1963-1968 (Box 3)
    - 1969-1973 (Box 3)
  - Room Allocations, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Schedule Copy (Box 3)
    - Fall, 1967-1973 (Box 3)
    - Spring, 1961-1972 (Box 3)
    - Summer, 1952-1972 (Box 3)
  - Search Committees, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Self-Survey Committee, 1964-1967 (Box 3)
  - Telephone Service, 1968-1972 (Box 3)
  - Twentieth Anniversary - School of Letters, 1967-1970 (Box 3)
  - University Press Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - University Study Committee, 1967 (Box 3)
- University - General, 1949-1973
  - AAUP (Box 3)
    - 1964-1969 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Tenure, 1954-1964 (Box 3)
  - Administrative Notices (Box 3)
    - 1958-1964 (Box 3)
    - 1965-1973 (Box 3)
  - Admissions Committee, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Arts and Sciences - College of, 1968-1972 (Box 3)
  - Bureau of Educational Placement, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - Bureau of Facilities Studies, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Committee on External Fellowships, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Dean of Faculties, 1969-1972 (Box 3)
  - Fee Remission Policy, 1969-1971 (Box 4)
  - Foreign Language Examinations, 1965-1970 (Box 4)
  - Foreign Students, 1968-1970 (Box 4)
  - Foundations (Box 4)
    - General, 1949-1971 (Box 4)
    - IU (Box 4)
      - 1950-1961 (Box 4)
      - 1962-1972 (Box 4)
  - Graduate School (Box 4)
    - 1952-1967 (Box 4)
    - 1968-1971 (Box 4)
  - Horizons of Knowledge, 1965-1970 (Box 4)
  - Patten Foundation Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Registration and Enrollment Procedures, 1963-1971 (Box 4)
  - Research and Advanced Studies, 1965-1971 (Box 4)
  - Yeats Symposium, 1964-1965 (Box 4)